JavaScript has some built in functions
that we can basically apply directly on arrays.
And these are called methods and we can think
of methods as array operations basically.
So let's now learn some useful array methods.
And there are actually countless array methods
in JavaScript and in fact, we have a whole section dedicated
to arrays alone.
That's how important they are in JavaScript.
But in this video we gonna learn just some basic ones
that you really need to know and also so that you start
to get used to the idea of using methods on arrays.
Now, let's start by bringing back the friends array
from the last lecture.
All right, and now let's start with a method called push.
So the push method adds elements to the end of an array.
And so let's say, friends dot and then push
and then the elements that we want to add
to the end of the array.
So let's say Jay here, so push is essentially a function
and we can see that by these parenthesis.
So it's a function that we call and we call
that function really attached to the friends array itself.
And that's what this dot here stands for, all right?
So again push is a method which technically is a function
and we call that function directly on the friends array.
So the push function is kind of attached
to the friends array and if you're wondering why that is
we will once more learn that a little bit later
in the course, but there is a good reason why this works
and it's actually a pretty fascinating stuff.
So I hope that you're excited to keep continuing
to explore this course, until you'll really learn how all
of this actually works.
Now anyway, let's now check out the friends array
in the console, because this is really all we need to do
to add an element to the end of the array.
And indeed now we get the original array
that we had before plus the Jay element.
And you see that the length is now also four, okay?
so this actually changed, so it mutated the original array,
but that's no problem at all just like I explained you
in the previous lecture, remember that?
All right, now since push is a function here,
it can also return something.
So we already know that we can pass arguments
into functions and we did that here with Jay,
then the function can do some work and in this case,
the work that the push function does is to add the element
to the array and actually the push function does return
a value and the value that it returns
is the length of the new array.
So if we want to capture that data or that value,
we can create a new variable for that.
So let's call it new length and let's
then also log it to console.
And indeed, it is four so most of the time
we actually don't do this.
So we just push an element and call it a day
because usually we don't immediately need the length
of the new array.
But in case we need it, we don't need
to then calculated separately, we can simply take the result
of this function here store it into a variable
and then use that.
Great, now besides the push method which adds elements to
the end of the array, there's also methods to add elements
to the beginning of the array so that is the unshift method.
So unshift and so let's say we wanted to add John
right to the beginning of this friends array.
So again, let's check it out and so now it should
have five elements and the first one should be John.
And yeah, it is and just like the push method,
the unshift method also returns the length of the new array.
But in this case we are just not saving it
because we don't really need it.
Next up we also have methods to remove elements from arrays.
So this one here add elements, so let me just write
that here, add elements
and then we have some to remove elements.
And let's start with the pop method which is basically
the opposite of the push method.
So this means that pop will remove the last element
of the array, so let's write that here.
And this time we don't need to pass in any argument
and that's because there is no information needed really
to just take out the last element.
So let's try that, oh we didn't log it again to the console.
So let's just grab it from here and now you see
that Jay is actually gone.
And if we did it twice for example, which of course
we can also do then Peter should also be gone
and indeed, we removed Jay and Peter.
Now, again this pop method also returns something,
but this one doesn't return the length of the new array
but instead, it returns the removed element.
And so that can sometimes be useful
so let's call this one popped, okay?
And so let's log that one to the console as well,
so that is the popped element and we could do the same for
this first call, but as I said earlier, we don't always do
this because it's not always that useful.
But here I just want to show you direct how it works
and so the pop element should now be Peter.
So this first one here is Jay and then
the last one becomes Peter.
And so here in the second pop call, Peter is the one
that's being removed and so that's the element that's
then going to be saved into popped
and yeah, here it is, okay?
And finally, let's also remove the first element
from the array and so that's friends dot unshift.
So let's copy this one again, give it a save
and so now only Michael and Steven should be left after all
this manipulation, right?
Oh, and actually that did not work and that's because I did
a mistake, so unshift is of course to add elements
to the array and so this one here is called shift
and not unshift, so now it should work, yeah.
Once again we didn't need any arguments and once again
this method here will return the element that was removed,
so if we need that, we can capture it.
Next up, there is a very useful method that tells us
in which position a certain element is in the array.
So let's work with this smaller array that we have left.
And what we want to log to the console now
is friends dot indexOf and then we pass the element,
which we want to reference.
So let's say we want Steven and so as I said
this should return the index at which this element
is located, so we know that Steven
is right now element number one, right?
So zero and one and we actually can see
that here in the console.
So zero is Michael, one is Steven so this indexOf function
call should return the value one, because again that's
the indexOf the element Steven and yeah, there we go.
Now, if we try the same thing for an element that
is not in there, let's say Bob, we will get minus one.
All right, and now finally to finish this lecture,
there is a very similar method to the indexOf,
but which is a bit more modern
and in my opinion also more useful.
So this one is an ES6 method and it's called includes.
So includes, instead of returning the index of
the element will simply return true if the element
is in the array and false if it's not.
So let's check that, so friends dot includes and now
we can actually do the same as up here.
So let me just copy that and the difference here is again
the includes method, so let's see what we get now.
And as expected with Stephen it is true because indeed
we have one element here Steven but Bob is false
because well, there is no element called Bob.
And this method actually uses strict equality
for this check.
So let's say that we pushed some value here to this array
so friends dot push which remember will add a value
to the end of the array.
So if we added 23 and then if we checked for 23 to string,
it would not work, so it would say false, right?
And that's because it is testing with strict equality
which means that it does not do type coercion.
And since 23 to string is different from 23 to number,
it gives us false, but if I test it directly for the number
then it should be true and yes, it is.
So we added it here to the array and so then of course
the array includes it, that makes sense.
And so we can use the include method to write conditionals.
So that's one of the very useful application of this method.
For example, just to test it out very quickly,
let's say friends dot includes Peter and then
if so we can log to the console,
you have a friend called Peter, okay?
So we already know that this here returns a Boolean
and we also already know how the if statement works
and so only if this is true.
So if the array does include a string with Peter,
only then this code is executed.
And so right now of course nothing happens
but if I ask for Steven then here let's say Stephen as well.
Then I get, you have a friend called Stephen.
So that's probably the most use case of the includes method.
Now right, and that's all I had to show you for
this lecture and as I said in the beginning,
there are many more useful methods for manipulating arrays.
But for now, I just wanted to show you the most basic ones.
And next up, there's yet another coding challenge
waiting for you.